Women have historically been paid less.
历史上，女性的工资一直较低。
But in the US in the 1980s, they began to catch up—fast.
但在20世纪80年代的美国，女性开始迎头赶上，而且速度很快。
During that decade, the gender pay gap closed by about one percentage point a year.
在那十年间，性别工资差距每年缩小约1个百分点。
Had that trend continued, the gender wage gap would have been closed by 2017.
假如这一趋势一直延续下去，性别工资差距到2017年就已经消除了。
But the trend didn’t continue, and the gap remains yawning.
但这一趋势并没有延续下去，差距至今依然悬殊。
According to a new study from academics at Harvard, the stagnation can be put down, perhaps counterintuitively, to the introduction of state and federal family leave policies.
据哈佛大学学者的一项新研究，这种停滞可以归因于州和联邦层面推行家庭假政策，这一点或许有违直觉。
The academics argue that during the 1990s, as governments began to introduce leave policies, it was mainly women who took advantage of them.
这些学者认为，在20世纪90年代，随着各级政府开始推行休假政策，利用这些政策的主要是女性。
Though the leave policies might have helped those women to stay in the workplace—instead of dropping out to have families—those who returned saw their wages had increased at lower rates than the men’s.
尽管休假政策或许帮助了这些女性留在职场，而不是离职去生儿育女，但休完假回到工作岗位的女性发现，自己工资的增长速度低于男性。
After family leave was introduced in the US, in fact, the rate of gender wage convergence fell to just 0.03 percentage points per year, and has remained there ever since.
事实上，美国推行家庭假之后，性别工资趋同的速度降到了每年仅0.03个百分点，此后一直停留在这一水平。
Those monitoring the process towards salary equity at work have long watched as progress slowed in many countries around the world.
长期以来，追踪职场薪酬公平进程的人眼看着世界上许多国家的进展放缓。
In fact, that progress began to reverse during the pandemic.
事实上，在疫情期间，这一进展开始倒退。
The gender pay gap is one of the most outstanding examples of that lack of parity, and still exists just about everywhere.
性别工资差距是这种不平等最突出的例子之一，而且几乎在所有地方都依然存在。
The motherhood penalty has become a shorthand for describing why: In many places, especially rich countries, women earn the same as men until they reach their childbearing years.
“母职惩罚”已经成为描述其中原因的简略说法：在许多地方，尤其是富裕国家，女性在进入育龄期之前，挣得和男性一样多。
Women who have children begin to see their salaries slip behind their male counterparts’.
有了孩子的女性会发现，自己的薪水开始落后于男性同行。
Part of this is because women take on more of the unpaid labor at home, which can eat into time available for work and energy for career advancement.
部分原因在于，女性在家中承担着更多的无偿劳动，这可能会挤占她们可用于工作的时间和谋求职业发展的精力。
But it’s also because mothers are passed over for raises and promotion, and because time out of the workplace sets women back, even if that time is taken voluntarily, and supported by company or government policy.
但这也是因为，母亲们在加薪和升职时得不到考虑，还因为离开职场的那段时间会让女性落后，即使这段时间是她们自愿休的，并且得到了公司或政府政策的支持。
What would have happened if leave policies hadn’t been introduced?
如果当初没有推行休假政策，情况又会怎样呢？
The study doesn’t go into that question, other than to say that if the 1980s trend had continued, we would have been at parity by now.
这项研究没有深入探讨这个问题，只是说，如果20世纪80年代的那种趋势延续下去，我们现在就已经实现平等了。
It’s possible, however, that the journey towards wage parity would have stalled either way.
不过，也有可能无论有没有休假政策，通往工资平等之路本来都会陷入停滞。
If women’s gains in the 1980s were made through the erasure of things like bias, once those less uncontrollable problems had been addressed, there would still have been an issue with women—who are the ones to bear children and take care of them in the early weeks because of biological factors like the ability to breastfeed, forcing them to take breaks, whether or not those breaks were mandated.
如果说女性在20世纪80年代取得的进步是通过消除偏见之类的问题实现的，那么一旦这些不那么难以控制的问题得到解决，女性仍会面临一个问题：由于哺乳能力等生理因素，生孩子并在最初几周照顾孩子的都是女性，这迫使她们暂停工作，无论这种暂停是不是强制规定的。